Reuben Moreton Curriculum Vitae

CONTACT DETAILS

Flat 4, 19 Granville Park London, SE13 7DY Telephone: +44 (0) 7791 567 182 E-mail: reuben.moreton@open.ac.uk

ABOUT

I am a subject-matter expert in forensic facial identification and image analysis, and have provided expertise operationally to police investigations and strategically in transformation projects. I have attended court as an expert witness and provide training and guidance on facial identification from imagery to police services and government departments in the UK and abroad. I have published peer-reviewed research, standards and best practice in forensic facial recognition and am a proactive member of international practitioner working groups. I am also an academic researcher in the psychology of forensic face matching and collaborate frequently with universities on research projects. I provide guest lectures in forensic science and have acted as a technical supervisor to students for undergraduate and postgraduate research projects. I am proficient in data analysis and visualisation using R.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Qumodo (2019 - present)

A company that researches, designs and develops human-centred artificial intelligence and technology.

Identity and Biometrics Lead (2019 – present)

I provide training and consultancy to police forces and government agencies in the UK and internationally on facial identification. I also lead on Al and human-factors consultancy projects, using qualitative and quantitative research techniques to produce client-ready white papers and technical reports for customers in policing and government.

Metropolitan Police Service (MPS) - Forensic Services (2009 - 2019)

Forensic Services delivers operational support and guidance to investigators and the courts in the recovery, analysis and interpretation of evidence. I was the Forensic lead for facial identification and imagery and provided expert advice in maximising forensic and biometric opportunities from imagery for the MPS, government and external partners.

- Forensic Capability and Change Manager (November 2017 2019)
 - Developed strategic design documents and business cases for senior stakeholders, acting as the business lead and subject-matter expert. Coordinated a multi-disciplinary team and advised on how to improve the use of forensic imagery and CCTV through automation and process change.
- Senior Forensic Facial Examiner (November 2011 November 2017)
 - Established a team of six forensic facial examiners, designing training, testing and processes based on empirical research, literature reviews and best practice. Acted as both line manager and mentor to the team, developing and operating a quality management system. Attended court across the UK to provide expert opinion evidence in facial identification and image analysis. Advised Forensic Services and other business areas across the MPS in the effective use of facial imagery and biometric technology.
- Digital Forensic Technician (September 2009 November 2011)
 - Provided operational support to investigations by the recovery and processing of video and images. Conducted casework-based research to provide tactical solutions to operational issues.

PROFESSIONAL GROUPS

European Network of Forensic Science Institutes - Digital Imaging Working Group (ENFSI-DIWG)

Facilitates the exchange of information and data, develops best practice and standards and runs human performance testing in image analysis and identification for forensic organisations across Europe.

- Quality and Competency Committee Liaison (2012 2019)
- Facial Comparison Lead (2012 2018)
- Secretary (2011 2012)

Facial Identification Subcommittee - Organisation of Scientific Area Committees (OSAC)

Develops consensus standards and guidelines for facial identification in the US and recommendations for research.

Affiliate Member (2014 – present)

Facial Identification Scientific Working Group (FISWG)

Standardises best practice in facial identification, facilitates cooperation between international agencies and disseminates guidance.

Member (2012 – 2018)

Reuben Moreton Curriculum Vitae

EDUCATION

PhD Psychology, Open University (2016 - 2021)

• Thesis title 'Expertise in applied face matching: training, examiners, super matchers and algorithms'
The focus of my research is to improve understanding of human and machine expertise in face matching and
its impact in operational environments. I have completed a wide ranging literature review on forensic face
matching expertise and current training practices, as well as qualitative data analysis, including an evaluation
of the face matching accuracy of forensic examiners, police officers and facial recognition technology.

MSc Forensic Science, Kings College London (2008 - 2009)

• Distinction and awarded prize for best research project by the British Academy of Forensic Science My research project evaluated a metric-based approach to facial identification, uncovering inherent limitations in the accuracy of the technique. The findings were published in 2011 and have led to best practice documents recommending the technique no longer be used.

BSc (Hons) Forensic and Crime Scene, Bournemouth University (2005-2008)

First

I presented the findings of my dissertation project into forensic age-estimation age at the American Academy of Forensic Sciences in Washington DC.

PUBLICATIONS

- Bindemann, M. Claydon, J. R. Fysh, M. C., Prunty, J. E., Moreton, R. *in prep*. Facial comparison behaviour of forensic facial examiners.
- Moreton, R. 2021. Forensic face matching: Procedures and application. In M. Bindemann (Ed.), *Forensic face matching*. Oxford University Press.
- Moreton, R., Pike, G., Havard, C., 2019. A task- and role-based perspective on super-recognizers, British Journal of Psychology, https://doi.org/10.1111/bjop.12394
- Towler, A., Kemp, R. I., Burton, A. M., Dunn, J. D., Wayne, T., Moreton, R., White, D. 2019. Do professional facial image comparison training courses work? PLOS ONE, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0211037
- European Network of Forensic Science Institutes, 2018. Best Practice Manual for Facial Image Comparison¹
- Metropolitan Police Service, 2016. Forensic Image Comparison and Interpretation Evidence: Guidance for Prosecutors and Investigators Issue 2.²
- Moreton, R., Morley, J. 2011. Investigation into the use of photoanthropometry in facial image comparison. Forensic Science International. 212. 1-13 (231-237)

RECENT NOTABLE CONFERENCES

- Unfamiliar Facial Identification Group 2020, University of New South Wales, Sydney. Presentation and poster Training and expertise in facial comparison
- Facial recognition conference 2019, INTERPOL, Lyon, France. Presentation Human operators and facial recognition systems
- Biometrics Congress 2018, London. Panel moderator, 'What is a super recognizer?'
- Unfamiliar Facial Identification Group 2018, University of New South Wales, Sydney. Keynote speaker, 'Good practice in facial identification: Bridging the gap between academic research and practitioner working groups'.
- Facial Recognition at its Best Workshop 2017, University of Notre Dame, London. Speaker and panel member, 'Operational use of facial imagery'.

REFERENCES

Robin How Serious Fraud Office

Head of DFU 2-4 Cockspur Street, London, SW1Y 5BS

Previous Line Manager Email: robinhow@gmail.com

Prof. Graham Pike Open University

Professor of Forensic Cognition Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences, Walton Hall, Milton Keynes, MK7 6AA

PhD Supervisor E-mail: <u>graham.pike@open.ac.uk</u>

¹ http://enfsi.eu/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/ENFSI-BPM-DI-01.pdf

² https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/511168/Image_Comparison and Interpretation Guidance Issue 2.pdf